Finding Aid for the E Clampus Vitus Records LSC.1796
UCLA Library Special Collections
E Clampus Vitus Records
1935-1970
UCLA Library Special Collections
E Clampus Vitus (Fraternal order)
LSC.1796
2 boxes (1 linear ft.)
1 oversize box
The revival of E Clampus Vitus was begun by Carl I. Wheat and others around 1931 as a parody of mining fraternities of the nineteenth century. E Clampus Vitus events were organized around historical anniversaries or in a place of historical significance. The collection consists of correspondence, membership rosters, and artifacts related to events and activites of the California chapters of the Ancient and Honorable Order of E Clampus Vitus.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lindley Bynum.
Gift of Andrew Horn.
Gift of Ward Ritchie, 1957.
Gift of Estate of W.W. Robinson.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9912179103606533
Biography
Revival of E Clampus Vitus was begun by Carl I. Wheat and others around 1931 as a parody of mining fraternities of the nineteenth century; E Clampus Vitus almost always organized its events around historical anniversaries or in a place of historical information; a history of the organization can be found in the book, Credo Quia Absurdum (Placerville, California: Onager Press, 1949).
Biographical Narrative
The history of the Ancient & Honorable Order of E Clampus Vitus is given in the book Credo quia absurdum (Placerville, California, 1949). The present social organization is a revival of mining fraternities of the nineteenth century, parodies of the then-popular mysterious fraternal orders. The present organization delights in the mock-serious aspects of the originals.
E Clampus Vitus almost always organizes its events around historical anniversaries or in a place of historical importance, so that keepsakes and announcements offer historical information, as well as providing records of the club's activities. Often the keepsakes are printed by noted California printers, such as Lawton Kennedy.
Prominent Californians were involved with the revival of the organization in the early nineteen-thirties, so that the history and papers of the organization are important in a study of California. Carl I. Wheat was one of the first to start the revival, around 1931. The present collection is made up of items donated by Lindley Bynum, Andrew Horn and Ward Ritchie; and of items from the W.W. Robinson collection.
note: Because of the completeness of materials collected by W.W. Robinson held in the Department of Special Collections, items taken from that collection have been stamped with his name. Other items not pertaining to the individuals above have been distributed throughout this collection without indicating the donor.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of correspondence, membership rosters, and artifacts related to events and activites of the California chapters of the Ancient and Honorable Order of E Clampus Vitus.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Materials with notes to or by W.W. Robinson, Lindley Bynum, Andrew Horn, and Ward Ritchie (Box 1)
Statewide (Box 1)
Platrix (Los Angeles) chapter (Box 1)
Other chapters (Box 2)
Events (Box 2)
General publications and newsletters (Box 2)
Oversize documents and keepsakes (Box 3)
E Clampus Vitus (Fraternal order)--Archives.
- Materials (Memorabilia, Notes, Correspondence, etc.)
  General note
  With notes to or by the following:
  - W.W. Robinson, 1949-51 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Lindley Bynum (Officer of Platrix Chapter), 1949-57 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lindley Bynum. Correspondence, much of it dealing with the workings of the organization, 1943-58 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Andrew Horn, 1950 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ward Ritchie. Early membership mailings, 1935-36. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ward Ritchie, 1949-50 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Statewide
  - Rosters, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Printed items, reports, announcements, etc., 1947, 1955, mostly n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clippings., 1940, 1948, 1953 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Platrix (Los Angeles) Chapter
  - Rosters. Printed, 1953, 1956, 1960, 1963. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Rosters. Mimeographed, 1950-51 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Draft: Initiatory ceremonies of the Ancient and Honorable Order of E.C.V., for May 21, 1949 conclave. 8 leaves. Carbon typescript. Initiatory Ceremonies of the Ancient & Honorable Order of E.C.V., Platrix Chapter. 10 leaves. Mimeograph. Initiatory ceremonies of the Ancient and Honorable Order of E.C.V., Platrix Chapter. 3 leaves. Incomplete carbon typescript., n.d. n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Petition for membership forms., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letterhead samples, printed envelopes., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letterhead mailings, 1949-57. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Announcements of events, mimeographed or small., 1935-49 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Announcements of events, 1949-58 and n.d.; Legal size or larger. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Announcements of events, using old newspaper mastheads, 1954-61 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Reservation forms for events, 1950-55 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous enclosures sent with announcements. Mimeographed maps, historical notes relevant to sites visited, etc., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Postcard announcements, 1936-39. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Postcard announcements, 1941-44; 1946-49. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Postcard announcements, 1950-55. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Postcard announcements, 1956- and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Keepsakes., 1960-61, 1970. (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Other Chapters
  - Hangtown (Placerville). Printed roster, letterhead sample, announcements, etc., 1938-58 and n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Yerba Buena (San Francisco). Letterhead samples, newsletters, keepsakes, etc. Includes items printed by Lawton Kennedy., 1936-57, 1962. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Las Plumas del Oro. Announcement, (County Centennial) and, 1954 1956. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Downie. Membership application, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Matuca. Announcement, 1949. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Specific Events
  - Coloma celebration, 100th anniversary of the discovery of gold, Announcements, programs, newspaper, etc., 1948. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Mariposa Centennial. Announcement, reservation forms, brochures, newspapers., 1954. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Fresno. 100th anniversary of Fresno County, Announcements., 1956. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- General Publications, Newsletters
  - Announcements of E Clampus Vitus publications., 1935, 1937(?) 1949, 1956. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - The Clamper: Official Publication of the Ancient and Honorable Order of E Clampus Vitus. Stockton, California, 1961-. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Scope and Contents note
    vol.1 no.1-6; vol.2 no.1-5; vol.3 no.1-4; vol.4 no.1,2,4.
  - The Hewgag Brays. Cedar Springs, 1962(?)-May 5, 1962; September 29, 1962. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Mariposa Gazette. Mariposa, vol.83 no.1. Has headline: Official Organ of E Clampus Vitus., June 4, 1936. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - The Placer Herald: Official Organ, Ancient and Honorable Order of E Clampus Vitus. Auburn, Placer County, California, Saturday, vol.83 no.40., June 1, 1935. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - The Pony Express: Stories of Pioneers and Old Trails. Placerville, 1934(?)-. (Box 3)
    vol.16 no.8-9; vol.17 no.2,8-9; vol.18 no.2,11; vol.20 no.3 (These issues 1950-53).
- Oversize Announcements, Keepsakes, etc.
  - Various chapters, v.d.